Hey there, I'm Emma from mmmEnglish.
We're coming up to that time of year again
when there are lots of events and celebrations.
That means lots of mingling,
lots of chatting to people that you don't know
and making small talk.
It happens at work, at gatherings with friends
or friends of friends and families of friends,
neighbors, even people that you bump into in the lift.
We've got to practice these skills.
With small talk, we can build rapport with our colleagues,
make new friends and just generally feel more positive
about the interactions that we have with other people.
So today, I'm gonna take you through 30 questions
to make a small talk, to build the confidence
to start conversations in English.
But before I do, I wanna give a quick shout out
to Lingoda who are sponsoring today's lesson.
If you want to overcome your fear of speech
and you want to do it quickly,
then you need to hear about the new three month challenges,
the sprint and the supersprint.
Both of these new promotions help you to commit
and take massive action to level up your language skills
in just three months.
And both give you the chance to get a refund
on the fees that you paid for your classes.
So what's the difference between the sprint
and the supersprint?
The sprint challenges you to take 15 classes a month
for three months in a row.
Complete that and you get 50% refund on your course fees.
The supersprint challenges you to take 30 classes per month
for three months.
Complete that and you get 100% refund
on your tuition fees.
It's that simple.
I took the Lingoda Marathon
and it was one of the best things that I've ever done.
I practice my Spanish every day with native teachers
and I earn real certifications.
Lingoda is a quality language school
which is of course why I recommend them to you.
With small group classes available 24 seven,
the flexibility is a huge plus.
The next sprints are happening from January to April.
What a way to start a new year,
especially if you end up getting that refund, right?
So if you think you've got what it takes,
secure your place by signing up by December 19th.
You need to pay 49 euros as a deposit
and if you use this code,
you'll get 10 euros off that deposit.
All the rules and event details are on the Lingoda website
and of course I'll put the link to that
in the description below.
Small talk is an incredibly important function
of English conversation.
It's about comfort.
It's about helping two people,
you and the other person that you're talking to,
to feel comfortable with each other.
And the intention is to try and find some common interests,
something that you can share together.
So I wanted to think of yourself as a detective.
You're searching for some information and some clues
to help you connect with someone,
to find some common ground and share interests.
A good way to approach small talk
is to focus on a few broad categories.
Work, life, travel, food and the weather.
Now I'm gonna go out on a limb here
and say that about 90% of all small talk conversations
focus on these topics, maybe even 95.
But this is great because it allows us to focus
on some really specific topics, right?
And help you to prepare for conversations
that you're very likely to actually experience.
There's another thing that's useful
to keep in mind with small talk and that's time.
With all of these topics,
we can ask questions that relate to the current situation.
Now, any experience in the past
or any future dreams or future plans, right?
So pay close attention to the examples
that I'm gonna share
because I'll be using some different time references
and any questions.
So let's get started with 30 questions
to help you master small talk conversations.
Starting with work.
Now, the most common question here is, what do you do?
So we're talking about now, what's their current job?
Imagine that the person that you're talking to
said they're a nurse.
But we wanna ask some more detail, right?
We wanna find out how they can continue the conversation.
So let's go back in time.
What motivated you to become a nurse?
Did you always wanna be a nurse?
What was your first ever job?
Did you like it?
We can talk about the present as well.
What does your typical workday look like?
What do you love about your job?
And you can get a little creative
with some future questions as well.
So is this your dream job?
Are you working towards something else?
I'm gonna be careful here that you don't say
working towards something bigger or something better
because it might be a little offensive, right?
You're sort of saying that their job
that they currently have isn't good enough.
If money wasn't an issue, what job would you want?
Some people might say that they don't wanna work
if they didn't have any issues with money, right?
But you might have to rephrase that question and say,
well, what would you do?
Or how would you spend your time?
Another really great small talk topic
is just talking about life.
And there's a couple of ways that you can do this.
You can pay attention to local news headlines.
This is a really good way of finding things to talk about.
Did you hear about the accident on the freeway last night?
Sounded awful.
I got stuck in traffic for over two hours.
Albeit you might end up talking a lot
about all of the negative stuff that was in your news, right?
But you can also ask questions
about what's happening in a person's life.
So remember that your intention is to try and find
some common interests, right?
Some things that you share
so that you can keep talking about those things together.
Have you got much planned for the weekend?
This is a great question.
It's my go-to.
Everyone loves talking about their plans on the weekend.
What do you like to do in your spare time?
Now, if they share something that you also like,
that's great because you can keep talking
about your shared interests.
Or if they share something that you don't know anything about,
ask them for more information.
Oh, that's so interesting.
I've never met anyone who keeps bees
and makes their own honey.
How much honey do you get each week?
Have you ever been bitten by a bee?
Is it easy to keep bees or do you have to be an expert?
Have you read any good books lately?
Have you seen any good movies?
If you're a mom or you're a dad,
you might even ask, so do you have any kids?
Because this is a great way to connect with someone.
Talk about your kids' ages, interests,
maybe even their minority habits.
Same thing with pets, actually.
Have you noticed that I've been using so quite a bit
to introduce a new idea to a conversation?
This is really quite a natural way
to introduce a new question.
One that's unrelated to what you've been talking about
previous, it's a really helpful conversation tool.
So are you from here?
This is a great question to help explore someone's past,
go back in time.
Where did you live before this?
Is this city quite different to that city?
Where did you grow up?
Travel is a great small talk topic.
It's something that we love talking about
and we love sharing.
So we can talk about our past experience
or we can talk about travel plans
and dreams for the future, right?
If you're coming up to a holiday season,
you're heading into summer,
then a great conversation starter is,
so are you planning on getting away for the holidays?
Are you taking time off over Christmas?
Or whatever holidays coming up?
But if it's not that time of year,
you can easily start a conversation
by introducing some context, right?
By sharing your experience first
and then inviting their input.
So I've just got back from the trip to Japan.
Have you ever been?
Or maybe you might know something about their experience.
You went to Peru last year, didn't you?
I'm planning on taking my fiance to South America in June.
It's our first time and I'm not really sure
which countries we're going to visit.
Do you have any recommendations?
Do you have any recommendations
about which country to visit in South America?
I am thinking about a trip next year.
I love traveling.
I hope to visit Kerala in the south of India
at some point soon.
What places are on your bucket list?
I'm actually really keen to hear your answers
to this question.
What places are on your bucket list?
What places are you dreaming about visiting?
Make sure you let me know in the comments.
Just like travel, food is another great small talk topic.
It's something that we all have in common.
We do it at least three times a day.
So there are plenty of opportunities
to start a conversation about food.
I'm trying to decide where to go for lunch.
Do you know any good restaurants around here?
I'm cooking lasagna for dinner tonight.
What about you?
Hey, have you tried that new Thai restaurant
on Church Street?
That's amazing.
Do you like Thai food?
Now, I just can't leave weather off the list.
This is the absolute number one small talk topic.
It can be used as a simple passing comment, right?
It's a beautiful day today, isn't it?
Can you believe all the rain we've been having lately?
But you can also use the weather as a way to spark a conversation
by using it to introduce another topic or another activity.
It's pouring out there.
It's a shame I rode my bike today.
How did you get to work?
So there you have it.
30 different questions,
30 ways to start a conversation with small talk in English.
Now, I'm going to set a little homework for you,
a little challenge, okay?
Because memorizing and practicing the questions
that I've shared with you today is one thing.
That's great practice.
But of course, what you need is to be ready
to answer those questions as well
so that you can keep the conversation going.
So your homework is to think of your own answers
to these questions too.
Once you ask them and then you hear the answer,
you want to be ready with your own experiences
and your own opinions to share, right?
To keep the small talk going.
If you'd like me to make some conversation workouts
about each of these topics, just like this one,
then make sure you tell me in the comments.
That way we can practice asking questions
and responding to them out loud together.
We're going to focus on tone and pronunciation
to help them come out really naturally.
And don't forget to check out Lingoda.
The link is in the description below.
Remember to use my code to get 10 euros off your deposit.
If you saw that before December 19th,
you can find me on Facebook and on Instagram.
If you don't follow me on Instagram yet,
then come and check it out.
This is where I share a little bit of personal stuff
about my life and about the amazing people that are in it.
If you're ready to keep practicing with me now,
then come and check out these lessons here.
I think you're gonna love them.
I'll see you in there.